[music]
Hello friends with you again audio greetings of the
podcast currently without a name my name is
Bohdana Neborak next to me Anastasia
Evdokymova we are at poetry readings
Meridian Chernovits which
are happening this year despite But in the war next to the
war so that we can all
reflect a little more on all that what
is happening with us and we also
continue to talk to you and record a
bonus episode of our podcast
to finally answer the questions
we received from you Because our
audio living room is very large and
has enough space for everyone and for those
who write about the war for those who read about the
war, and more precisely for those who write and read
during the war, in particular about us and you
Hello everyone and in fact we have another
opportunity to record this bonus episode because there is
one such magical prize which is
aptly called And actually you can enter and
vote for your favorite
currently untitled podcast, just move your mouse
or touchpad and you will be able to do a lot of
fun let's meet with Bohdana because we put
a lot of effort into making our
podcast better and more interesting and our
dialogue with you continues. Yes, this is also an opportunity to
support a Ukrainian-language podcast about
culture, and I am convinced that
it will be a great pleasure for everyone in this audio lounge.
Join and vote.
at the award it's right And we roll in
[music]
We invite our first listener to our audio lounge,
who comes in with his
glass of wine, sits down and asks, dear
God, Anastasia, my name is Oleg. Thank you
for currently no name at all. Thank you to the
editors of Day Ukrainians for other tips.
when there is a war,
I feel that this concept is undergoing changes both for
me personally and for my friends and
people close to me, so I would like to
ask for your advice on what
to read, watch and listen to
from modern authors of art
and Ukrainian artists on this topic in order to
be able to to somehow think more deeply and more
about these
variable meanings Oleg Thank you You are with us.
Thank you for asking about such a complex
category. As a home, at the beginning of April, I
gave a lecture on Frankivska, even about this,
against how literature Ukrainian
literature
understands the concept of home, the concept of this
archetype, the concept of this concept, this is a
cultural concept, because it is a certain
space constructed by hands and a certain
space you dreamed and invented by those who
live in it, by those who create it, who
fill it, and I understand that all of us Ukrainians
during this time, during these six months, faced
different categories of home, home, forgotten
home, lost home, found home, and
each of us had the opportunity to
live with these categories
to exist with the understanding that our home
can be forgotten It can be
lost It can be found Also in
Ukrainian literature there is a theme of homelessness
when the heroes have no home and They
are looking for a place to settle down And where to find this home and
where ZAZ to settle and start
building his from scratch, for example, Taras
Shevchenko dreamed of his home and he wrote
about the fact that home is a certain R ay, this is a certain
model at the end of life already in the 1860s,
for example, he had a beloved liquor store,
he dedicated various texts to her, there is a
text and there he says I will build a house and a room
and a garden, I will plant raisin trees. That is, you need to
find this space of your own and even drew
it, modeled it this house, which should be
somewhere near the Dnieper on a bend on his land,
and the house of Taras Shevchenko is such a
starting point. In order to talk
about home in Ukrainian literature in general,
because Ukrainian writers found houses, they
lost them, so the
hero of the demotonovych in the novel of landlessness
who returns to his hometown in his native
Katerynoslav Dnipropetrovsk, he thinks about
what his home is like, because modern people have
generally developed the habit of not having their own
corner, not having something to which they can
tie themselves, not having their own soil,
it's romantic, it's as if something was
quite fashionable and trendy, it seemed that
if you you can put everything in one
shoulder bag, everything that is important to you in your
apartment, then you are cool because you can
be found anywhere, not everything turned out to be it's so
simple, so not everything is so simple, because Natalya Humenyuk,
for example, writes about the lost home today
in the collection of reports "The
Lost Island" when she writes about the Crimea,
and those Crimean Tatars who, for example,
were forced to leave their home, also write about the home
, and authors who consider the topic in the
house, the word and for example, there are novels by Yura
Maryna Grimychki, which became extremely popular
at a certain moment and received
literary awards in Ukraine a few
years ago, and these are novels about writer's
houses, in particular, about the Rolid
house, which is in the center of Kyiv at the intersection
of Bohdan Khmelnytskyi streets and some other
street, I forgot which house the house is
writers, where writers lived,
Soviet writers, where they
gathered, where later
generations of their descendants lived, and what intrigues
took place around these houses, that
is, in fact, Ukrainian authors constantly returned to the topic of the house,
and here it is important to
find someone who resonates with you, who
speaks like you, there are a lot of us
listeners and listeners who listen to us behind the
scenes Dons who are far from their home or
for whom Ukraine is a second home and such
listeners can be advised
to listen to Vasyl Makhna's text home in baiting hollow, because
Vasyl left his native Ternopil region a long time ago,
but he constantly mentally
returns to his Chortkov, he writes
about Manhattan but thinks about Ternopil
he walks along the Mississippi but
thinks about his native Zbruch. And actually,
these echoes are constantly present, because even
authors who are far away from
home still express themselves in them.
Is the ambassador for Ukrainians a
mussel? Do you have access to these secret
audio rooms in the Facebook group? Do you
have the opportunity to listen to this conversation? Does
Bohdan remember any other
texts about home, about this feeling of home,
in addition to the fact that we actually talked about
homelessness in Serhiy Zhadana's boarding school
this is our second episode. It was only the beginning,
but then we talked about Mr what is this Pasha
This teacher has no place to
return to In fact there is no place to
which he would be attached that would be
important enough for him to be an
argument Why he should complete his
odyssey I really liked the selection of
texts that you suggested But when I was
listening to Oleg,
I immediately remembered that we
recently had an interview with Oksana
Zabuzhko on Ukrainians, which I was lucky enough to do, and
my original idea was to
ask Oksana Zabuzhko why she
wrote her two novels and what she
wanted to achieve with them, and when we when they came
to the topic of the Museum of Abandoned Secrets,
Oksana Zabuzhko immediately said that
she would like to write a novel, The House, because
she felt that we lack such a novel.
It will be big, it will have
many rooms, a certain number of floors, there
will be balconies, amphitheaters, and so on.
She wanted it to be like this You could
dive into the novel, hide, interact with
it as we can with the house, because again, the
house is different spaces. There will be a sub and
there will be an attic, there will be your children's
room and a locker in which you hid some
artifacts from your childhood. Well, and so on.
you, Nastya, have also
repeatedly repeated this incredible
famous quote by Heidegger about the fact that language
is the home of being and I constantly feel this
now, especially these For more than six months, I
think many people who work in a certain way in a
conspiracy feel it now,
so for me the most honest answer
will be that for me, every cool text in
Ukrainian is a text about my home
and I feel at home in it.
I think you should continue this conversation about
home, about Ukraine, about important topics.
day My name is Oleksiy, I am from Kyiv, although I
left Kyiv a long time ago and have been living
abroad for a long time. First of all, thank you very much
for I listen to the dcast, I re-listen to something, I agree with something, I
agree with something, I argue with something, I debate
right while listening,
but the most valuable thing is that it is interesting.
And here are the
episodes in which people talked about the city of
Pidmohylny about
Andruhovich's Muscovyate, and I began to think
about the geographical territorial dimension of
Ukrainian,
special Ukrainian modern
literature there. For example, Halychyna
Prokhaska and Andruhovich.
words as it is
spoken
meaningfully from reflected Ukrainian
modern literature and thus traveling through the
literary map I thought about the
region we are all thinking about now The
last few months especially our
south Ukrainian south Ukrainian
Crimea Sea of ​​Azov ske black Southern Bug
Ingulets Dnipro River Danube Dniester in the
end
Berdyansk-Mariupol Melitopol Kherson
Kakhovka
Mykolayiv Odesa Ankerman Izmail and Crimea and
Crimea and Crimea well, this Ukrainian south,
how are they manifested, how are they manifested
or how are they manifested in Ukrainian
literature, what is this south when I
talk about that's what I
was thinking, a book by Olesya Ulyanenko came to my mind,
where the south is, the book is gorgeous, it
just amazed me once and I thought about
the master of the ship Yuriy Yanovsky, well,
it's from
our twenties, er, I started
rereading it and you know it's gorgeous,
just gorgeous, the book is gorgeous literature,
listen to such a great question, it seems to me, of
course, I am not running away from the
answer, but in fact,
we need to focus on each region and
talk about what literature described
this region, which authors were local and
what they wrote, which authors came
somewhere and were inspired to write about a
certain region we more or less
know this about Lviv very poorly,
for example Mr Kyiv is still our capital,
we may know a little about Donbas, but this
does not become a common property.
you will have such a
close raising And we will also watch the
movies Klaus Zlochin and then we will
listen to music, that is, we can
have such a super immersion. I think this is a
great idea for the next season,
if we are talking about the south. Thank you,
Oleksiy, for this question, then of course we
now from our virtual audio shelf we will
get the books that you mentioned
first of all because Oles Ulyanenko is an author
who definitely needs additional
advertising and additional conversation because he is an author
who won the Small
Shevchenko Prize in 1997, he is an author who
deserves to be read by us because in
he has fantastic texts. If you
want to know the Holosiivo district
as it is, as it was in the 90s, from
absolutely with them social types and types, of
course you should read Lesya Ulyanenko's Stalin.
If you want to know Kyiv
zero, then this is the flowers of Sodom, and if we
are talking about the scary in places and
banditry at the same time despairing
precipice, as well as Mykolaiv, then you should
read Where the South is, a novel in which the
author Oles Ulyanenko gives a certain Faith
Faith in his heroes because there are very few chances that
they will have a better life, chances for a
future, even less than
the heroes in his boarding school, but
still he wants to support his teenage hero,
he believes that this hero can
break out of this environment from the circle of all
these bandits and drug addicts, that he can
change his life because he is still young, but
whether this hero and some of his prototypes will be able
to accomplish this is what
remains in question, this is a
completely different story, and of course there is the story of the master
ship, a fantastic story about
Oleksandr Dovzhenko, Yuriy Yanovsky and the
Odessa film studio, such a romantic
image of Odessa and what love is
there are triangles, all the film studios, and what are the various vicissitudes, because Yanovsky is really a master of words, and the master of the ship is a novel that fascinates. If you want to read about summer Odessa, read the master of the ship, but it is also worth mentioning Tangier by Ivan Kozlenka, another novel about Odessa in which Kozlenko works with this a myth Where Odesa is not spelled with two letters s why for so long all of us active in Ukrainian culture fought with one C And this is a certain Ukrainian Odesa So this is a cool example and a very good continuation of Yanovsky because Kozlenko actually writes the history of Odessa in a not so alternative way, but This as with many discussions in those cities where both the Russian and Ukrainian components were present. When you want, you can tell the story of Odesa quite pro-Russian, and Dmitry Bykov, who for years came to Odesa and did exactly that, but you can tell the history of this city. Just like Ivan Kozlenko, you know I am very grateful to him for actually offering us this alternative takes one of the
first steps and shows that this is also
possible, it can be continued, it can be
introduced into pop culture in
various projects in which such a story of Odesa will be told,
there is a
very cool article by Yaryna Tsymbal on the website lyakcent, about
various reports, the first Ukrainian
reports of the 20-30s x years, we will leave
this article in the description for the episode, and it says
that in fact Ukrainian
writers of airport studies wrote a
lot about sea voyages, voyages to
distant unknown crews, and Among such
voyages, it is worth noting the artistic
text of Mykola Trubylaini,
Schoona Columbus, the text that is today
even in the recommended literature for
reading in school, not in the school
program, but in extracurricular reading, a
text in which there is also a sea, there are waves, there is love,
there is delight and the sea - It is, of course, black
, that is, there are enough works that
have this Primorsky wipe and
it is worth looking for them only among modern
literature is it worth talking about the classics. Because
when we say the word Kherson or the
Kherson region of course, we
immediately think of the Dnieper seagull, and the easiest thing
to read is her novella wave, when
we talk about the sea and waves, we
also talk about Lesya Ukrainka, she has not only a poem called a
wave with a
fantastic rhythm and rhyme, which is a
stanza that moves as a
wave moves on the sea because she is a wave that roars and
attacks. And you can swim in this whole whirlpool for a
very long time, but in one of the
first poetic cycles of Lesya Ukrainka,
Journey to the Sea, there are
texts about Odessa, but the heroine of this
lyrical cycle moves from the north. She
moves from her native Volyn, she says goodbye to her,
says Farewell my Volyn, I am
leaving you for a long time, it moves through
Podillia through the steppes and eventually ends up
near the sea, and the
largest number of texts in the
cycle is dedicated to this
coast.
where the heroes go to the Crimea and
describe this Crimea so well that
you immediately want to see this I don't need to
breathe this salty air, in fact
there are quite a few texts about Crimea too, if we
thought about making a
selection of poetry that would be dedicated
to this Crimean Ukrainian
peninsula and what he gave to Ukraine, we would
very easily collect a lot of texts by
first-rate authors but
I also remembered a text that
our listeners might want to read, a text by
Oksana Zabuzhko called Crimea,
Yalta Farewell to the Empire, a
very interesting poem for the continuation of our
decolonial practices. Since we
talked about poetry, I want
to invite our listener Anna, who
also has a question
Anna. Please come in. Good afternoon,
my name is Anna. Thank you for your advice. There
are
many authors of works for
me. The question is how to love poetry. And
is it necessary to love it at all if I
like to read prose. Thank you. Thank you.
in
that it seems to me that there should
be problems with reading old relationship and if you
don't want to and don't like reading poetry
She doesn't work with you then it's absolutely
normal and there's no
problem with that,
however if you ask this question then
you probably want to try
reading poetry too What the
more you read it the better the better you understand how
it works, the more you have
intertexts that allow you to
connect threads, because let's say it's very
difficult to understand Serhiy Zhadana if you don't
read before that,
well, at least Mykhailo Semenko and Yevhen
Pluzhnyk, although you can certainly
enjoy Zhadana's texts and without
this understanding, it is very important to find
your voices and it is important to try your authors and authors
who will work with you,
and if you want to
try, I think there is no better option
in Ukraine to try to read poetry than the
anthology of Ivan Malkovich from Tychyna
very Dan, which as such contains even quite
voluminous selections of cult and canonical
Ukrainian
authors, and sometimes a text or two are simply very
cool works by individual authors that
Malkovich selected for his ontology and
this is a kind of tasting, you can
bookmark a page at a certain
stop and move sequentially.
poems, try to record for yourself what
you observed there, what you felt, and then
there are really high chances that poetry will
speak to you very unexpectedly and
offer you something. And after familiarizing yourself with the
classics, open the next anthology, an
anthology of the third millennium, where the
authors of modern Ukrainian
young poets Myroslav Leyuk are collected a Ukrainian poet was also the
editor of this book,
and there you can try to
understand how
those who live in the same city with you think and feel the world.
Maybe even on the next street and with
whom they resonate, because you have overcome
this path from Tychyna to Zhadana, so now
continue your move forward you know I
od once I remembered Well, when I think about the poems
About Kyiv, I can't do anything with myself,
because in my head there is not Mykola
Zerov, not Mykola Vingranovsky, even on the
TV-grave in my head Dmytro
Lazutkin, who writes This city knew all
my kisses, this city heard All my
songs I don't know if you are listening to me now and whether it will
speak to you in the Kyiv sense or
not, but I am immediately touched by a poem that will
definitely speak about this poem of another friend.
it's good
when a bottle of champagne doesn't break,
especially if it's full
[music]
with a full glass of champagne,
our next listener comes to us. Or rather, a
listener. Hello, my name is Sasha. I
really like how you talk about what you talk about.
in the context of
experiencing the Ukrainian psychological
collective trauma associated with the
Russian-Ukrainian war And my
question is as follows:
Pidmogilny is still considered, as far as I
remember from my school days, one of the first
existential writers at the level of
Sredghir. I really feel
that way when I read the city, especially the
communication with the critic Vyhorsky, and do
you think that this is really so? Do you think it is possible
that this is the signing of
Ukrainian writers under some
world standards that were not needed.
This is simply an individual story of
Pidmohylny, which he tries to
tell without the influence of any
European existential trends. Because
it seems to me that this is not the case and that Pidmohylny's work to a
large
extent
influenced the
world development of existential
literary legacy to Oleksandr
Thank you for listening
to us, we can actually look at the
writer as we readers want.
And there is also specialized
literary studies, which has different types,
different approaches, in fact, there is the theory of literature,
which offers us a multitude of different
approaches to how to look at a writer
sometimes and always more precisely for a
literary critic, the context will weigh and the
fact that the author does not arise by
himself, he acts in a certain coordinate system,
we know that Valerian Pidmohylnyi
read a lot of foreign literature,
in particular French-language literature, we understand that he
kept his finger on the pulse and understood this nerve of
French literature, we understand that
Podmogilny was extremely gifted
and his own genius, his own nerve
was extremely powerful and he himself
felt this world and styles and directions do not
arise only under the influence of each other
or under someone's influence, they arise
due to a number of socio-political
circumstances and some trends which, roughly
speaking, greet in the air about
existential motives,
Pidmohylny wrote entire PhD
theses, the most recent one was protected and
checked in the 19th year in Lviv, which
is called existentialism in
Valerian Pidmohylny's work,
urges you to find and read it, because it is
written about what there is a state of
absurdity head I'm sick of what I feel. The feeling of freedom
in the characters of Valerian Pidmogilny. I also
thought about such a thing that
when we talk about good literature and the
texts of Valerian Pidmogilny, this is very
good literature.
We never talk primarily about
style or genre. They always
follow the good. literature, if
first of all we want to talk about
genre or style, then in my opinion we are
talking about
craft, which can also be of high quality, but
for me once became such a very
striking example
that I can no longer remember where I read or
heard, but it concerns the genre of
detective stories and novels Umberto Eco, the name of the
rose Well, we're not talking about the fact that
Eco is a great detective author, we're saying
that this novel is very good, that is, it is the novel that defines
us, according to a good idea, which is
wrapped in good literature and where is everything else.
And this is generally a cool way to check
texts It seems to me that when we really
want to clearly segregate it and
put it in some drawer,
then this approach is quite cold and in the Bible for some
reason Father,
it seems to me that I have gone too far and this
is not at all in the context of your question,
Sasha, but I would probably just like to
say about it, I am convinced that
Pidmohylyny's
existentialism simply follows the fact
that it is important for him to speak, and it is important for
him to speak, well, as Khvylovy
wrote what he said I, too, went to the age of the
Undertaker, he felt it very well and
wanted to record this dignity, and
therefore, due to a certain sadness that he felt,
potentialism also came. Thank you very much. We
can move on
. that's
why there are many familiar faces in our audio lounge. And
in general, we know and strive to know all
our listeners and listeners face to face, so
write to us, give us your feedback on
social networks,
join us to read, listen
and watch what we recommend with us,
join the community for ukrainians
mussel to be with us on the same wave
to participate in reading clubs in various
activities to be with us in the same eco-
ecosystem. But if we have already chosen you, then
if you just join the community
for Ukrainians Media. There you will find
other like-minded people, not Bohdan and Nenastya, and
actually.
I already had help,
fortunately, to ask a question during the recording of
Kyiv Leyla, then I asked about
what to advise foreign Ukrainians to
read in order to discover
Ukrainian literature from scratch or anew,
and developing this topic, I
would like to ask you
about how you see the path of transformation
school education in the direction of literature,
because now we have an
unprecedented chance to change the
vector of the education movement
to fight against those distorted peoples who,
unfortunately, often formed a completely
different picture of the perception of Ukrainian
literature in children, how can we take advantage of this
chance, how can each person, in turn,
influence perhaps even the state
institutions or mechanisms at the Ministry
in order to be in correct changes to the
program and, in general, how to make these changes
ecological, thoughtful and balanced, so that
they have an effective result and we
can raise a really conscious generation
that understands and perceives in the correct and,
let's say, adequate way,
Ukrainian literature of the grove. Thank you for this
question, I want to recommend an article about the
same often think and which is very accessible,
this is an article written by such a
literary critic from Australia, a
Ukrainianist, Mark Pavlyshyn, which
is called the Canon and the iconostasis, and in this
article Pavlyshyn explains the difference
between the approach to literature in the context of the
Canon of formation, such a healthy
approach and the
iconostasis, where does the iconostasis come from, it
arises in the post-Soviet countries where
portraits of Lenin were conditionally removed and
instead they moved the portraits of
Franko Shevchenko and Lesia Ukrainka a little to the pile of
those authors who were allowed to sleep
all those who were repressed and simply
revealed their names,
there was no work with cult
authors who were in the school program but in
Soviet times, which required
rethinking, there was also no
work with shot revival, it
all changed slowly, there were fantastic
projects, I can list dozens of them,
but here we should definitely name the
project our twentieth, which was led by Yaryna
Tsymbal in
cooperation with Tempora publishing house, in
order to simply open this era and
wrote a bunch of very popular articles, this was
constantly done by Vira Ageeva, whom we
mention when we talk about these three great
figures Shevchenko Ukrainka Franko I
immediately think of the titanic work
done by the house of Franko in Lviv, which is headed by
Bohdan Tikholos Who was not or who was I
advise everyone should go to Franko's house when you are in
Lviv, take tours and remind yourself
that the
technical inspector likes to repeat that this is the
real home of a living man, but they
have wonderful projects that relate to changing the
false image of Franko that was built by
Soviet Propaganda, in other words, this is a project
that shows that Franko is not only
a stonemason, he looks not only like
yo th tombstone at the Lychakiv
cemetery Well, he certainly does not fight for
communism on the territory of Ukraine, in the
literary critic Tamara Gundorova there is a
work called Franko is not a stonemason.
if it all boils down,
then for me the problem is that
you just need to read the works and build a
personal relationship with them so that they
can be included in the school curriculum and
become, if not loved, then simply
read by children; if the texts are not read,
they are not reflected upon, there are no constantly
updated reflections, but simply as a range
, some old interpretations are accepted that have
barely changed over the past 30
years, then our affairs will be blocked because
no one is engaged in actual reading,
reading is a creative process, we all
remember that there are three factors of the
literary process: the author, the texts, the
readers and they are equivalent when we
exclude the reader from this process so there
is nothing left, literature
as such is actually absent, so I would
be happy if the texts
were really read and discussed in schools, and on the
other hand, well, we actually have a lot of
problems with
important literary figures,
I think to myself that
while, for example, the
Minister of Culture and Information
Politicians are incredibly worried about the fate of
Bulgakov, but do not
initiate, let's say, projects about Kyiv
Pidmogilny or Kyivdomontovych, then it
will not be easy for us either, although
there is no shortage of independent initiatives and we have listed some of them,
but this
clichéd political will is very important and until the
political will is directed to
reform of school education and the humanitarian
direction of school education, unfortunately,
it will be very difficult to change anything. But
fortunately, Germany still has
some allies in the form of
some teachers who know how to fall in love with
this literature despite all the challenges of the
school curriculum every time there
is a conversation about the problems
of its school curriculum disadvantages of her
week my eyes start twitching
because usually it's a conversation You know
hang around the tables in Facebook communities
while with some completely
unfamiliar people, some find out that Oh
yes, you have teaching experience Oh yes,
you have some relation to culture and
so on yes or to literature,
explain to me why it is like that and I
get very tired of these conversations very quickly because
it is difficult to explain to people
what this mechanism is and it is really big
and complex, you cannot take it and click your
fingers and change the entire school program,
why is it impossible because in order to
change the school program is not enough to say.
Let's now read Yuri Andruhovich,
let's read Yuri Andruhovich, or
let's read All of Modern
Literature in two months, let's
read all of Modern Literature, and the
next question is that Okay, but Someone
should sit down and write a methodical material
with recommendations, exercises, and specific
tasks to guide this teacher
who is reading and learning this modern literature for the first time
a calf who has probably been working
at a school for the last 30 years and even
had to relearn from a teacher of
foreign world literature first to
world literature from foreign
literature, that is, from Russian to world
from world to Ukrainian
and all, in fact, all these people, all
teachers need to be given specific
tools, we study this text is
specific for the purpose of Why it
violates Such topics There are such types of heroes There are such
conflict situations that we already
went through in the course of the seventh grade and now
in the ninth we return to it or
we observe the evolution of the genre and
we understand something for ourselves we can see something, and here the
most important thing is for the teacher to use these
tools to show it, to
see it really in the first place, there was
and will be reading for all those who
whine to me that it is impossible, how difficult it was for them to
read. Are the oxen roaring like a manger is full?
I ask if you have read this
essay already at a conscious age. Okay, are you
lucky in quotes or unlucky?
itelko is something else. This is a separate question,
it is a question of your educational institution, the
choice of your parents, or what kind of
conscientious or conscientious student you were,
and here is the question of whether this
work is harmful for children. Well, you
reread it as an adult, because those
adult conscious teachers who today
there are also from the younger generation at school,
they understand that this text Are the
oxen roaring is actually a text about a personality, a
bipolar psychological disorder, which
has always been this Chipka, the way he is
because he had a difficult childhood, he
is the way he is because the circumstances around him are changing
And they he is pressured to
re-read Do the oxen roar like the manger is
full return for yourself to the problems of the
Kaydash family Understand what they are
return to the Christmas carol in prose at the
end of Dickens before Christmas to
see
this Scrooge with all his faults with
all the faults of society around because
now in your adult conscious age
when you still have such a resource
called Goo gle, you will be able to read for yourself
even more about the times when
Dickens lived and what Dickens writes about And what
were the
social problems around Scrooge and what were the social problems around Scrooge And
you will open a whole incredible world
13 you are talking about such a thing that is very difficult to
formulate without sharp and which consists in the
fact that there are many different problems that
relate to the literature course in the school
curriculum,
but at the private level they cannot be
solved without a personal desire
to discover something. You can
live indefinitely within the framework of certain vulgar
clichés about literature, not necessarily
Ukrainian but in principle, what is reading? Well,
everything that is taught in school is boring, or
to return to our well-known
stereotypes about Ukrainian literature,
which is all about the village and serfs,
there is no other and everyone just wails and
suffers, but to disprove the stereotype,
you have to want it, and this is where it starts
the space of personal choice, which in
fact not everyone is ready to do in
adulthood, although they can and a
pleasant discovery will await them then, but
I would really like these changes in the
methodology of studying this literature in
schools, because it is a chance for children to not
become victims of these stereotypes anymore, and
it is terribly tempting to me. I am sure that
you are also in this work that we in the
context of our literature, we make it
possible to stop some harmful
processes and focus more and more
on reading and reflection for everyone
who wants to reread and get
qualified pedagogical support for
rereading literature for the 9th grade.
I invite you to the platform of the all-Ukrainian
school online because for the 9th all the lessons were
read by your servant Ms. Anastasia
Yevdokymova to the class, and therefore everything is explained there
absolutely perfectly. No, this is probably not the right
word.
Let me do it myself, because you somehow
choose these words so dear listeners. Those
listeners of the podcast currently have no name. I
think that I have already she told him,
you know, stories from life, they come to an
end, and to the child, but
Ms. Nastya was reading uro that even
I am Astafieva and Olya Polakovi, and I
did it skillfully, so we should also
contact Nastya for Panas the Peaceful, and the keys to
Panas the Peaceful are with Mrs. Nastya somewhere in the
pocket of her dress.
I think we can move on to our
last question to our listener
who is sitting here on the edge of the sofa.
By the way, this is our friend Yana, and what is she
asking us? Hello Nastya, hello Bogdana.
This is Yana Superovska in your
audio living room. This is how I virtually
walk in and sit on the sofa nearby. By the way,
I want to tell you that
I always
associate your audio living room with those salons of the Old
World that we have lost, now I
imagine myself almost in the salon of Lyudmila
staritska Chernyakhivska, where once
these discussions were held, where new ideas were born and
so on, this is such a very cool lost
but also returned experience.
to relate to what was
lost but what one wants to
return for obvious reasons We
are talking a lot now about
decolonization about fasting imperial experience
about the return of everything that Russia
stole from us over the centuries and so on.
And these are all very necessary and correct
conversations, but
the more I talk about it with different
people, the more I see such a special
thing that there is a significant part of people and it is
really significant who talks about who
does not understand the need to return it all who is
ready to protect let's not move
let's not touch what to do with people
who are not ready to colonize themselves
After all there are many of them and we have to live with them and we
somehow have to influence them or what
to do with life with those who chose not to just
passively observe, but to resist in
order to purify themselves and finally become
normal Ukrainians. Thank you, Yana always
does such a thing, which she knows very well,
it raises a difficult question. And here I, Nasty,
immediately began to think about the fact that
many people really do not want to
to change not even because it's convenient or
comfortable, because it's usual, but for me the
answer to this is no, I'm not, the question is such
a simple thing, it's important that those who
make decisions can influence
certain changes and be agents of change with
ministers of state, that they be ready to
change,
decommunize space and decolonize
themselves when necessary, because
people accept changes and we understand that
people accept changes very quickly,
street name changes, memory changes changes to the
bas-reliefs,
changes to the program, at first everyone
criticizes the changes because they are difficult,
they are painful, and in principle, well
, the world worked, the world worked normally and
differently, but I would really like to
have people in our government who understand the
importance of changes, because these changes determine the
space which will be Ukrainian and not
also Ukrainian. I was once very touched by the
story of how at the opening of
the Shevchenko monument in Lviv, Ihor
Kalynets said that he would very much like
Ukraine to be the same for Ukrainians.
Finally, the time has come for
Ukraine to be
at the forefront for Ukrainians. We
talked a lot about what it means to be
Ukrainian political choice It does not depend at all
on
gender, race, country of origin,
ethnicity,
it is a political choice to call yourself
Ukrainian, to
call yourself Ukrainian is to adhere to
certain values ​​and protect them as
Ukrainians do today, and that is why I
would very much like us to
worry about these political Ukrainians,
because we actually thought about others for a very long time,
and these others were the Russians, it
was how not to offend the Russians, how not to
provoke the Russians, how not to make the Russians
think something wrong.
Michael's golden tower is not the
one we see today, but the one that
was blown up by the Bolsheviks in the 1930s because they
just wanted to, because they didn't care about the
history of Kyiv, and I decided to look for
some materials because I thought, Well, in the 90s, there
must be certain references on the Internet about
how these elements returned and it is clear
that in fact the Minkul of that time hesitated for a very long
time whether it was necessary to turn to the Russians
and to return Ukrainian cultural
heritage, Ukrainian cultural heritage and
our physical expressed history, for a
very long time we were in a situation where
we were convinced that to ask for our correction
is not even to ask, but to say that it is
yours by right and should be with you in your
home, this is wrong, indecent,
inconvenient with us until now they are trying to
continue this rather poor
manipulation when they are trying to
convince us to solve the
Russians' various issues, to satisfy their cultural
needs, psychological needs, emotional
needs.
on
this occasion, in one of our episodes,
we even talked about the return of
stolen artists and it is important to remember that we
return not only artists, but their works,
and next to the return, there are also donations
that we are ready to give. Do you remember we
talked about what Russian-language
hits by An and Lorak, we are ready to give, but in
return there is so much that we
need to take back, and it applies
not only to this era of Zelenskiy, the period of
oblivion is very old. Because the first
written monuments of Ukraine, the Russians are the
Ostromir Gospel or the congregations of
Svyatoslav are never on the territory of
Ukraine they were not here in the sense that they were
brought out even before the time of Catherine II,
they settled somewhere in different monasteries,
different palaces, and I find it so strange and so
sad that the first monuments that show the
Ukrainian language, Ukrainian literature,
Ukrainian writing, book writing are not here,
not here we can see copies,
maybe the originals are not so important, as
for the monuments, they have long been
scanned, everything has long been read by
scientists, but for a very long time, scientists
who researched this ancient
literature
had to travel by land somewhere to deep
Russia, or in principle to Russia, in order
to read it in order to
create this Ukrainian
cultural discourse of ours, and there were monuments to
which there were none were allowed and it is quite possible that we will
not see them and our children and grandchildren will not
see them because Well, unless Russia
falls apart, which we usually indulge in, in the end, we
actually want to give you our dear listeners of
the currently untitled
pkst a new tip, I give ukrainians
this podcast by the author and the scriptwriter of which
is Yana Superovska, this podcast
is called the cultural tribunal.
Yana talks in an incredibly playful manner
about
what and how we could give back, we
need to give back, and she really
models this tribunal. Here we are in the mood to
record the podcast and from the territory of
the Meridian festival black by I here this
idea also floats,
but we will need to speak at
those tribunals that will finally happen because
We talk a lot about this gag, which has already
become just
such a
cliché that
justice must be done. It must be done, but
we understand that it must be so. But we
do not know when it will be in its prompt the
cultural tribunal of Ian on various
examples of
id artifacts Hey, the names of the narratives are
trying to find out, firstly, why
to return, secondly, what and how to return,
it even reminds me a little of the
beginning of the census of what we need to
return to ourselves by right, because it is ours.
to have fun like me,
you will definitely like the podcast or
I get special pleasure from the scripts,
so subscribe to the
cultural tribunal and follow the
updates. By the way, Yana's flowers are also very
cool, she writes. That is, you can subscribe
at once in many places, friends, we
really enjoyed talking
together with
it was very difficult for you in our shared audio living room to
select your questions and give some
attention, but we are still limited by the
space of this podcast, thank you for recording them,
because we had the opportunity to listen carefully to
everything and be well inspired before the
start of our
second season. But before how will we
continue this pause for the autumn holidays?
We need to recover,
no to gather strength and reflect a little on the
format of Ukrainian culture, which
is worth listening to, watching, reading, which
is worth watching and following so much
that we are ready to continue these conversations for an
infinite time and, of course, in this
process to look for our name, because at the moment we have no
name, and we do not understand how to call
ourselves how to call the processes and phenomena
around us.
So see you soon.
We will talk to everyone. And don't forget, friends,
don't forget what you need to vote for.
Tell us. Ask your friends to also
vote for the award. It's right that a hint
about Ukrainian culture should not
just be at the top. And everyone should understand that
culture is not what's in the moment, but it's
just in the vanguard. We're voting for everything, currently
untitled, see you
[music]